okay let's start good afternoon everyone
it's my pleasure to welcome you to cc
ends challenges and controversies
session where we will collectively
discuss and hopefully debate the
free-energy principle so as you may know
the free-energy principle or act of
inference has been developed and applied
in the neuroscience community for the
past 15 years particularly in the field
of cognitive neuroscience and
psychiatric research and somewhat in
parallel it's developed into a good
model and robust debate amongst
philosophers particularly there in the
field of consciousness research and
embodied cognition and even more
recently the framework has reached
formally into physics where the maths
have been unfurled to reveal
Schrodinger's equations Maxwell's law of
electromagnetism and wave particle
duality and this is all afforded by
dynamical Systems Theory and Markov
blankets where spatio-temporal
recursions of a single idea the drive to
minimize free energy speak speaks to
thickness across multiple scales from
quantum phenomena to large active
particles like ourselves so today in
this session I hope we can cover the
core concepts and mathematics and its
implications for the study of the human
brain and cognition and the format for
the next hour and a half we'll see
introductory remarks from our
discussants for 15 minutes or 20 minutes
apiece followed by hopefully a lively
debate and Q&A from the audience so
there'll be no provocation here of our
Parliament and to facilitate audience
participation we'll have one roving mic
and I've also set up a poll everywhere
channel where you can submit your
questions live now ordering the
introductions or during the discussion
via your smartphone or your laptops and
so to do this you go to poll evey calm
and enter a user name which is me
Rosalyn M 0 92 or you can go directly to
poll evey comm forward slash Rosalyn M 0
92 and it's written on the board's here
and there you can submit your questions
and I'll pass them to discussants
depending on how much time we have we'll
get through as many as we can if we have
a lot of questions I'll be updating the
live pose so be patient if the poles
fill up be putting a new pole on the
same address and do add your name and
institution to the end of the question
if you so wish okay - so to our
discussants they say that a good boxing
match is not based on opponents of
different abilities but on matching
opponents of different styles and so
today I think we'll have a very good
boxing match since in the red corner and
in the blue corner we have two
exceptional scientists who have in some
ways sympathetic views and ideas but
distinctive points of view so in the red
corner we have professor Christine Karl
is the scientific director of the
welcome to a center for human ear
imaging at University College London
Karl is the originator of the free
energy principle and you might say has
published extensively in the theory from
its development to applications across
the fields I've mentioned and in the
blue corner we have professor Jeff Beck
Jeff is professor of Neurobiology and
biomedical engineering at Duke
University and at Dukes Institute of
brain sciences and he is well known to
this community for his seminal
contributions to probabilistic coding
bayes in the brain and sensory motor
domains and also in higher cognitive
functions studying decision-making
across species so thank you both
sincerely for agreeing to come and
participate so from the rumble in the
jungle to the Thrilla in Manilla we now
have the Battle of Bayes in Berlin and
so with that for round 1 let's welcome
card first open
[Applause]
well thank you for our invigorating
introduction and it's clearly a great
pleasure to be here and I'm flattered in
a perverse sort of way you have to be
controversial I don't think I've
normally cast as controversial though so
that's good and the last time I had to
do something that was controversial was
to discuss different ideological
positions under the banner of NYX versus
Scruffy's I don't know if you if this is
a sort of an dichotomy which people are
aware of I liken this to a sketch a sort
of pre Monty Python sketch in England
where class wars were the thing in the
1970s and 80s and here we have John
Cleese and the Two Ronnies talking about
the class that they come from and this
tall gentleman here is upper-class and
he looks down upon this gentleman here
who is middle-class who in turn looks
down upon Ronnie Corbett who in this
sketch is very lower class and I'm gonna
make the position just to situate the
debate I'm gonna make the argument that
this hierarchy of ideological high
church nuts is paralleled in the NEETs
versus the Scruffy's and the Mystics
from our point of view I'm going to
associate the needs with physicists
people who are in search of simple
unifying neat explanations for
everything and I want to contrast that
with engineers who are the Scruffy's and
these are people who are much more
pragmatic and they want to know what
works so they will adopt anything that
works and from our perspective that
could be 20th century behaviorism
reinforcement learning drift diffusion
models temporal discounting if it works
use it and then we have the Mystics now
I usually have psychologists under that
but I thought the
you got to keep the crowd on the side
Avenue and so I've made them I've made
them philosophers we don't need to talk
about them any further so in four slides
my brief is false lies leave the free
energy principle so here is the free
energy principle in four slides at its
simplest it just says everything that
can change will change to minimize very
variation or free energy and that's
sometimes articulated written in
philosophy as self evidencing now free
energy here I've expressed in terms of
complexity - accuracy and that
mathematically provides an upper bound
on the quantity known as log evidence or
disc evidence or marginal likelihood
that's the probability of some outcomes
or observations given a model or my
understanding of how those those data
were generated so I'm going to focus on
this decomposition as a way of
understanding the role of minimizing
complexity whilst providing an accurate
explanation for the sensory observations
at hand and motivate the importance of
that just by unpacking the different
kinds of interpretation one can bring to
bear to understand what this quantity is
here the log probability of some
outcomes at some time possibly in the
future given a model of how those
outcomes were generated and if you
associate that log probability with
value what we're basically saying is
that minimizing free energy is the same
thing as minimizing a bound on value and
I should say if you come from machine
learning this is exactly the same as the
elbow or the evidence lower bound using
things like variational auto-encoders
but from point of view or psychologists
they could also be value they could be
the sort of expected reward that you
will obtain the
a particular course of action so this
can be regarded as a statement of the
imperatives that underwrite
reinforcement learning optimal control
theory and indeed in economics expected
utility theory so that's nice that
covers a large bunch of people there are
other groups of people who would think
more in terms of information theory so
the negative of this value is called
self information in information theory
also called surprisal and it is the
quantity that's upper bounded by the
variation free energy and minimizing
self information or minimizing surprisal
is essentially the same as maximizing
the mutual information and from that you
can spin off the principles of minimum
redundancy the principles of maximum
efficiency the infamous principle of
ralph olinska and or and indeed the free
energy principle itself that in turn is
nice because the expected the time
averaged of self information is known as
entropy so what we're saying is if
everything has to minimize its free
energy then it has to basically minimize
over time entropy and of course that is
the holy grail of self-organization in
physics synergetics of course if you're
a physiologist it's just homeostasis is
just keeping outcomes within
physiological bounds preventing the
dispersion and the tendency to disorder
that one normally attributes to the
second law of thermodynamics but there's
a final interpretation here which might
appeal to many of you in the audience
and that's is drilling down on this
marginal likelihood itself so if I
interpret M as a model of a journeyer
model of how these data were generated
then this becomes model evidence also
known as integrated evidence which means
that minimizing free energy is simply a
statement of the fact that or an
imperative to maximize the evidence for
one's models of the world and from that
we can develop the basic brain
hypothesis evidence accumulation and
things like predictive coding
and that's largely the perspective that
I'm going to adopt on free energy
minimization the rather move entailed by
the free energy principle which is
probably less familiar to too many
people it's not just about inferring the
best explanation for the causes of your
sensorial it's also inferring what
you're going to do it's also about what
are the best data or sensory samples
that with my active palpation of the
world I can gather together in the aid
of minimizing free energy or maximizing
the evidence for my own models and we're
appealing here to very old ideas first
elaborated by people like Lindley in
terms of optimal Bayes in design so it's
not about building good models of data
its what are the best data you can go an
actively sample from your world in order
to afford the best kind of inferences
about the causes and in that world and
that's formally can be articulated in
terms of perception being in the game of
minimizing free energy basically the
difference between your posterior
beliefs about hidden or latent states of
the world at some time possibly in the
future in relation to your true
posterior which is the bound and this is
the log evidence here so policy
selection in this expression here where
PI denotes a policy is all about
minimizing the free energy consequent
upon taking a particular policy or
acting on the world in a particular way
and all we need to do is to take the
average free energy under our beliefs
our posterior predictive beliefs about
the outcomes that would ensue if I did
that and if we apply that to the free
energy expression here we're now
conditioning on a particular policy and
we're just slightly relabeling and
rearranging the terms to express it in
terms of a
sure of incentives and vow and values
and I've written them down here in terms
there are a number of ways of unpacking
this and I'll do that in a second in
terms of instrumental and epistemic
value so what does that mean well if I
just focus on components of the terms of
the expected free energy and pretend
that we had a an agent or somebody who
had no particular prior preferences no
value extrinsic value or reward
preferences then we're left with these
two terms here and it turns out that
these are exactly or this is exactly the
quantity that's optimized an optional
Bayesian design and the visual
neurosciences it's known as Bayesian
surprise popularized I believe that
Christophe Kok an idiom balding and
mathematically that is exactly the same
as a mutual information between outcomes
and their causes in the future and of
course that is consistent with the
principle of maximum efficiency of
minimum redundancy articulated by people
like Horace Barlow let's just now take
two sorts of uncertainty out of the mix
and see what this expected free energy
looks like I'm hoping that you will
start to recognize the terms so the
first sort of uncertainty is basically
ambiguity I have no ambiguity about
what's out there beyond my sensations I
can see the states of the world directly
and that just leaves us with these two
terms here
they're basically score the difference
between what I will predict will happen
and what I prefer will happen and that's
known as a KL objective function for KL
control in optimal control theory or if
in economists it's risk sensitive
control to minimize the outcomes of
behavior in terms of my expected
outcomes in relation what to talk to my
goals or what I prefer to happen now I'm
going to take the final source of
uncertainty which is what will happen if
I do do that and if we take both source
uncertainty out we're right back to
reinforcement learning expected utility
theory so the expected outcomes on my
prior preferences under what I think
will happen
the point here is that these are all
internally consistent and equally valid
ways of trying to write down often
behavior but they are all special cases
of one imperative which is to minimize
the expected free energy or maximize
expected evidence for your models of the
world in the future I won't go into this
in detail
Roslin's is intimated you can extend
this argument right down to quantum
physics or right up to evolution and
many people have started to do that by
putting a Bayesian gloss on in
theoretical biology in terms of
evolution practically though I just want
to conclude with a comment upon the
explanatory scope and what this actually
means for people creating artifacts or
creating prediction machines to explain
say fMRI responses in the ventral stream
it is neat and simple that's the whole
point about being a NEET or a physicist
it's just basically saying what we have
to do is to provide accurate accounts of
our world or the sensed world that is as
minimally complex as possible thereby
maximizing the evidence for me as a
model of my world and this complexity
term is extremely important it's just
Occam's principle and from that we can
motivate certain factorizations that
simplify a giant in model of the world
you can get differential specializations
in your anatomical functional anatomy
that belies or speaks to that
factorization we can talk about
redundancy minimization the shape of
receptive fields that maximize the
information gathered from the
environment efficient coding and so on
we can also think about this from the
point of view of pragmatism and
economics what we're talking about
because we're using an evidence band we
talk about bounded rationality slightly
disingenuous use of the word bounded
rationality from the point of view in
the columnist but it's still bounded
rationality it's perfectly Bayes optimal
but it's using an evidence band and that
is the definition of approximate
Bayesian inference based upon free
energy bounds it also very gracefully
accommodates heuristics
that emerged in many different levels so
in economics it would be bigger ends and
like heuristics these are just priors
empirical prize that have inherited from
your parents or neurodevelopment
or some other form of Bayesian model
selection and if you're an engineer or a
physiologist then via the joinin scale
equality and Landau's principle is a
direct relationship between your ability
to minimize a complexity cost and the
algorithmic complexity that underwrites
the thermodynamic cost of erasing bits
so if you've got the three energy
minimizing solution you have a bound
upon the most efficient way to do it
whether you are dealing with the
cerebral blood flow as a physiologist or
whether you're actually designing
supercomputers and you want to minimize
the amount of electricity required to
solve a particular computation so that's
about it neat and simple evidence is
equal to simplicity plus accuracy as
Einstein said everything should be made
as simple as possible but not simpler so
there you have it thank you very much
indeed
[Applause]
[Music]
Thank You Carl next up we have no
sabotages so hopefully I see we're
getting questions through this is great
keep them coming so just to remind you
all it's pole Evie comm forward-slash
Rosalyn M 0 9 - well Jeff is getting
ready and has miked up to respond to car
sweet yeah we'll see
so no thank you
I have a word of advice for anyone who's
ever invited to do something like this
in the future read the fine print on the
invitation because I got this nice
little email and it said would you like
to debate Carl first inand I didn't
really read the whole thing I just said
to myself that sounds like a ton of fun
like what could be better but I was
under the impression that we weren't
talking about the free energy principle
as a unifying concept for a cognitive
computation but rather as a theory which
has created a bit of a problem for me
because as as a unifying concept for
cognitive computation Carl hiring I
think complete agreement this is to be
an incredibly boring debate so I'm sorry
maybe we'll throw something but it it's
not gonna get too much better than that
because we are as far as I can tell
largely in agreement on this question
there's another question the question I
wished we were addressing which is is
free energy principle unifying theory of
cognitive computation and I would say I
have a four type of very slightly
slightly different answer very different
answer which is somewhere between no and
not yet or it needs more you know it
there's it's it's it's not a complete
theory and I'll try to get I'll try to
explain what I mean by that at the very
end but because we're largely in
agreement on a lot of things first thing
I'm going to spend a lot of time doing
is addressing popular criticisms of the
frit what I'm going to call the free
energy framework instead of principle
because that makes more sense and I'm
not gonna refer to as a theory though
neither did Carl oh I noticed I was
tallying not a single use of the word
theory saw it coming oh sorry I'm gonna
put this down
so I'm gonna spend a lot of time just
talking about what are the common
criticisms of the the free-energy
framework and addressing them because I
don't think they're valid criticisms I
mean and we'll talk about why I don't
think it's quite a theory or may not be
a theory but it's nonetheless incredibly
useful okay so here we go so here are
the common criticisms of the free-energy
framework they largely center around
they don't center around things like
epistemic and intrinsic value those
words don't pop up very often instead
they they tend to take the form of
something more like wait a minute why it
why this obsession about surprise after
all there are very desirable things that
are very surprising so if I'm minimizing
surprise aren't I eliminating all of
these desirable things like winning the
lottery the second criticism comes with
oh and you know there's actually really
trivial way to minimize surprise you
it's known as the darkroom problem what
do you do if you want to minimize
surprise while you just stop sensing the
world
cover your eyes go into a dark room and
this has been a these Chris's have been
addressed many times I think most in
that's what was the name of the article
that was the conversation between the
philosopher and the physicist absolutely
lovely I had trouble reading it but I'm
gonna rephrase that as I go through and
I think like maybe planar terms I hope
but here's here's a little exchange that
made me chuckle this is one of Karl's
responses in a paper that he wrote years
a few years back addressing this sort of
issue regarding the active inference
part of the free energy principle so he
did something that made me chuckle
I thought it was hilarious and brilliant
in his actual paper he quoted a reviewer
and then directly responded to him this
was brilliant for two reasons so first
of all what better way to placate review
or two especially reviewer who'd use a
word like a lid than by actually
acknowledging his use of that word
publicly completely brilliant of course
the my second response to seeing this
was I had to look up what the word lid
was
it turns out it's actually pronounced
alive and what it means is to conflate
so 10 points for saying for knowing what
the word ye lid means and -5 for the
missed opportunity for alliteration
catastrophic ly conflating is a lot
better way to say that and here's calls
response I'm not gonna read Karl's
response you can read it for yourself
but I'm simply going to try to explain
it with a few examples ok so here's
here's how this goes oh sorry
there was a actually what's Karl's
response I will I will not read it I
will simply summarize it was to say that
that optimal behaved there are two kinds
of surprise that you have to worry about
when minimizing for energy an action
selection in an environment which are
also selecting your action one kind of
surprise is about the sensory input and
another kind of surprise is about your
action and it and/or is about yet is
about how surprising transitions between
states become and that's what I'm gonna
try Oulu say so here's here's a here's
the basic problem as a lot of people see
it in my opinion so this is a typical RL
type problem here's a mouse he's an
amazing ever been in this maze before he
has a massive amount of state
uncertainty because he didn't understand
the configuration of the maze he doesn't
know where the cheese is he doesn't know
where the walls are there's a massive
amount of uncertainty what does the
mouse do he begins by exploring his
environment so he zips around eventually
he finds the cheese and in an RL
framework he gets ten points he got the
cheese it's over you pick him up you put
him in another spot in the maze and then
what is the mouse do well he now knows
something about his environment so he
set has he says oh I know something
others environment now have an informed
policy that will get me from point A to
point B so I can get more cheese and
therefore more points there's something
that's missing from this framework and
they're no I'll just wave my hands
there's a step that's missing from this
simple RL perspective which is which is
yes there's a robot maxima doesn't we
reward in the free energy framework and
maybe that's a problem there's also
something missing what does the mouse do
when he gets to the cheese there's a
serious question he eats the cheese
right getting to the cheese yes it's
rewarding and you can model that as
reward but you can also model it as
suddenly having a great deal of
certainty about his actions he's not
surprised to find cheese he's sure he's
going to eat it I think that at a high
level I'm hoping to get a nod and I'm
not getting an OK at a high level I
would say that that is the difference
between the reinforcement learning and
what I would call like the this free
energy approach for an active inference
it that there is this there's two
notions of surprise that we're doing a
sensory surprise and and surprise in
your action space or surprise in your
transition probability space
matha apologize for the math but he
started it his here's a simple in a
simple Bayesian RL example I I'm sure
that many of you are familiar with this
that elucidates the difference between
or how policy and reward are related so
I'm going to frame this as a Bayesian
reinforcement learning problem so
initially you're a mouse you're in a
maze you have some you know in the
absence of a control signal which will
eventually be you you have some sort of
popu there are states that you would
transition between maybe just moving
randomly through your environment but of
course you could exert a control signal
and therefore U and therefore execute a
particular policy what you'd like to do
is you'd like to choose your control
signal so as to minimize it's tempting
it's so tempting so as to minimize your
cost or maximize your reward they're the
same thing how does that work well just
for simplicity because we want a simple
example with an explicit result we're
going to assume that the cost of actions
is simply measured in the KL divergence
between your you know sort of go with
the flow prior of just randomly moving
through states as opposed to as opposed
to exerting control as opposed observing
the control signal U and then of course
there is some cost or reward associated
with getting the Chi
or maybe just stagnating starving
whatever and we're gonna call that C of
s so that's like the cost of achieving
the state that is I suddenly or the
value of either not or achieving the
state though in which you have cheese
for example so these are logs we can do
math we move things around and what we
end up with is being able to show that
our expected cost or our expected the
negative of our expected reward can be
expressed as a kale divergence between
our policy can you see my cursor no of
course not maybe I should be using this
yes as the expected kale divergence
between our policy and something that is
kind of like a probability distribution
not quite there's some constants that
we're neglecting but they don't really
matter what we do is we're gonna find
the U that makes this as close to this
as possible what should we call this
right well okay we got it from this you
know sort of single state cost it ends
up looking something like this you can
call that your policy right you can call
that your policy prior right this is
what you this is how you should adjust
your control signal you want your
behavior to be like this to maximize
your reward or to minimize cost this is
the endpoint of this kind of reward
maximization calculation in contrast
this is the starting point of a free
energy framework you start with a policy
prior I'm sorry I'm Zack pick house as I
cannot use the word policy prior you
start with a default policy which says
how you would move from state to state
that you like that is consistent with
your goals but you've abstract it away
reward entirely you just have this
default policy so at the end of the day
what is called really cog yeah we'll put
it that what is called really done my
view on this is what he's done is he's
sort of come up with an equivalent but
slightly different definition of what a
decision-making organism is
so here's the standard decision-making
formulation right there's gonna be some
data it's going to come in to your brain
you're gonna do some inferences which is
going to be something how you represent
the world or represent your data and
then generate some action so what do you
need to do in standard decision-making
for you to have a few things right an
organism becomes defined by its
inference engine how it interprets data
from the world its defined by its reward
function and explicit and implicitly the
goal of maximizing reward okay this is
the standard way to do it and of course
what do you do with this information
will decide you find a policy that
maximizes your reward alternatively
within the free-energy formulation or
framework or whatever want to call it an
organism is not defined by a reward but
instead of defined by its inference
engine which is an approximate
distribution applied to a generative
model this is an important caveat there
doesn't have to be this is a little more
general in the sense that doesn't have
to be a generative model that informs
the affected that informs the inference
engine but there can be and a pal and a
policy a default policy what you would
do with you got to the cheese if you
knew nothing about the environment or
actually my brand we don't even know
about the cheese if you do find the
cheese your actions become very clear
and that that sort of thing is
incorporated into this sort of default
policy the probability of eating the
cheese given that you have cheese in
front of you and then of course there's
the aesthetically pleasing feature that
if you take this approach beliefs and
actions can be both selected by
minimizing a single objective function
which is called free energy it's pretty
so before I move on I just like to pull
the audience now not electronically
that's really intimidating just hands
what makes more sense like reward or
policy as a way of another equivalent
they're mathematically if you have a
reward function you can find an
equivalent policy that maximizes it and
to some extent vice versa it's a little
messy but it can be done but which is
better right well it's it's my view that
it's really hard to say I kind of have a
sneaking suspicion that from an
empirical perspective policy is a better
thing to think about because policy is
what we actually measure in the lab
so here's how do you measure reward well
you don't major directly you infer it
you put somebody in a room when you said
you want Snickers or skittles what do
you do you behave you perform an action
you say Snickers if you're a rational
human being now you can change this a
little by saying okay well okay skittles
or 75 percent chance of Snickers and
maybe get a better estimate of their
reward but at the end of the day what
you're actually measuring is people's
behavior it's the actions that people
are taking when placed in an unambiguous
state that is a policy you always
directly infer policies in an
experimental setting and never infer
reward directly right the reward is
something you compute from observations
of someone's policy so from an empirical
perspective this actually makes a little
bit more sense and so I like it
just a couple more things I have to
cover even though I think they're lame
so there's the darkroom problem I think
that some of these criticisms qualify as
lazy or - well now I shouldn't have said
that I take that back I think some of
these credits some of the criticisms the
phones of this category are too high
level for me to understand so minimizing
surprise is too easy there is a great
way to minimize your sensory surprise
you can go into a dark room you can
cover your eyes
you can simply stop participating in the
world and that's all fine and dandy now
there's the trivial response to this
trick this crazy criticism is to say
yeah that's not gonna last very long
right if you if you close your eyes you
will eventually die you will stop making
predictions and everything will be
surprising now there's a bit of a sticky
wicket here because if your actual prior
says with great likelihood you live in a
dark room your predictions will be your
prior predictions and they'll state
still be pretty good now we can play
this game forever
turns out oh right so the response is
well total surprise minimization
actually encourages life you wouldn't do
this okay so I call this the pit coward
joinder this comes from my good friend
Zack who's seated over there and is
probably going to bury his head in a
second when a paraphrase a little
conversation we had yesterday I'm gonna
change the words to make me look good
and
look bad but it goes something like this
what if I brought nachos into my dark
room where I'm blindfolded and my eyes
are closed I'm not going to die you
might need a few other things if you
wish to survive but at the end of the
day yeah that's what seems to be like a
perfectly acceptable solution to the
problem of minimizing surprise so what's
your problem Zach what's wrong with this
solution does that would say no exact
would say I would never do that and I
would say well I I mean it doesn't seem
that bad bring an Xbox you know that
actually sounds a lot like my personal
time that said other organisms find this
acceptable what the hell's wrong with
you Zach right so an example of this is
mold ah perfectly timed perfectly timed
done to pushing buttons this is a
perfectly acceptable solution to some
organisms that's one of them believe it
or not that's actually a picture of mold
on nachos so what's the next problem the
problem is is that his default policy is
the policy of a human being and not of
mold this becomes this is a perfectly
acceptable solution to this he's not
mold I'm pretty sure and so of course
he's not going to pursue that as a
solution but there are organisms that do
because that's their policy policy has
become something that now defines an
organism instead of reward and that's
really all I wanted to say so I hope
that at this point there you've come to
a few conclusions in a timely fashion I
would say that reward functions and
default policies are equally valid ways
of defining decision making organism the
free energy principle is nice in the
sense that it provides a general and
sensible mathematical framework for
description of inference and decision
making it's aesthetically pleasing and
so on and so forth I hope you draw 1/3
conclusion with this this is the worst
debate ever because I've just spent my
20 minutes talking about what's right
about the free and
principal or the free-energy framework
well that's because I haven't gotten to
the last man so it is the free-energy
framework I insist on calling it
unifying and I would argue that yes it
is it is precisely because it doesn't
make a lot of assumptions and most of
the assumptions that it does make you
can kind of squeeze other things into
right so here the fundamental
assumptions as I see it of the
free-energy framework right the brain
has a model that includes a policy it
has a set of accessible approximations
for the purposes of performing inference
an action selection which we call cue
right and inference an action selection
occurs simply by minimizing the you know
either klq P or free energy or whatever
you want to call it as a result of it
it's some incredibly general theory
right anything can be in court on
anything know anything I'm gonna stick
with anything just about any description
of a behaving entity can be squeezed
into the free energy from by judicious
choice of your model that you're
inverting p.m. which is what I called it
and your choice of approximations q
anything and I spent a lot of time
trying to think of things that you
couldn't include in the free energy
principle and I actually kind of
initially I sort the oh well you know
sampling based inference is a unique
kind of inference me know that you can
totally squeeze that into example what's
a sample after all right what can you do
with the sampling so you have 50 samples
what can you do with them well I can
evaluate free energy I can get a point
estimate I can take an average and to
the extent that my sampling scheme is a
good one on average free energy will be
going down using a sampling based
difference game okay so that that gets
in there too so we kind of leaned to get
rid of the what is not how about
non-bayesian schemes
totally you can get non yes this is very
busy in my definition there is a
Bayesian break we do take into account
uncertainty but maybe not always
how can you fit a non-bayesian scheme it
is well again by judicious toit choice
of Q right typically we like Q because Q
can contract variance and uncertainty
about the properties of the world that
we care about but why not pick a Q that
doesn't why not pick a Q that just says
oh zero entropy Q's that's all I'm
allowed now you're basically doing map
estimation and you're not behaving in a
Bayesian way that's
in there anyway so it can do anyway and
that's why I called a framework and not
a theory right it's great it's a great
mathematical language it's a language
that I hope we would all adopt because I
understand it it makes sense to me but
it provides very little guidance
regarding the things that I actually
care about right if there's no guidance
within the pen I could be wrong there's
no guidance within this framework for
choosing your generative models that the
brain is using there seems to be very
little guidance for choosing q there is
some I would not say there's none but
there's very little guidance for how you
to choose the kinds of approximations
that the brain is using there's as far
as I can tell zero guidance for the
optimization algorithm and so here's a
few that people like and more critically
at least to me there's almost no
guidance in terms of the relationship
between your beliefs in this case your
cues right and neural activity
it's simply agnostic and that's what
makes it a framework and not a theory I
just wanted to quote two peoples who
said very smart things and phrase things
much better than I could
Sam guess gee is Sam Sam Gershwin and he
his quote is that predictive failures of
the free energy he said principle I say
framework are typically attributed to
poor choice of your P's and your Q's if
you don't mind your P's and Q's but you
know you yes thank you I got one laughs
out of that one thank you Eric
if you don't mind your P's and Q's you
will make bad predictions and if you do
you can make good ones but that's not a
property of free energy it's a property
of your choice of models and an
inference algorithms and Ralph Hefner is
our H in this scenario he basically
reader the same thing using much better
words than I would have chosen that is
that thank you
[Applause]
[Music]
Thank You Jeff let's leave those up
shall we and Dimitri I'm gonna give you
a microphone so you can wander around
the crowd and look for questions and we
have some online and maybe we'll take a
few minutes for Carl to address some of
the points yeah this is fine thank you
that we just heard whichever you'd like
yeah thank you
well I thought you'd use all the good
words usually in the right order the and
I like that P&Q thing I never thought
about before so for those of you don't
know that comes from print in the old
days when they used to print and these
two have different blocks or P's and Q's
and when apprentices used to get them
inverted I also do prepositions and
questions the like it's just actually
literally is if he's getting the P's and
Q's right so to take your in to take
your lust I think you've identified a
number of really key issues and
unfortunately we're going to be in
largely agreement here so you have
framework I think is perfectly fine I
use the word principle because it's
essentially the free-energy principle is
just a variational principle of least
action you're formally mathematically
that is what it is but if you want to
use that to provide a framework within
which to house or consider various
process there is I think there would be
a very appropriate use of the word of a
framework but I slipped in there the
distinction between a process a theory
which may or may not be consistent with
the free-energy principle and the
framework and the principle itself and I
think you're absolutely right that you
know the the framework does not
prescribe a particular process theory
and inversion scheme and more crucially
it doesn't provide what we all really
want to know which is that the nature
and the form the physiology of the
implicit generative models to which you
apply the variational machinery under
the framework or the
support and I think there's a implicit
in some of your statements which I agree
with entirely was only so here is decree
cost to the complete class theorem or
theorems that say for any pair of
observed behaviors and loss function
there is a Bayes optimal solution so I
think you're absolutely right the
free-energy principle
cannot be wrong yeah it cannot be
falsified of course in the sense of a
variational principle of least action it
doesn't have the attribute of being
falsifiable but any process theory can
because to be a process sir you'd have
to write down the form of the Geritol
model what sorts of quantities entails
are you including inference about fast
hidden states are including learning
about slow model parameters are you
including structure learning are
including evolution so all of these
start to shape the form and separation
temple scales in the hierarchical form
of the Geraldton model at hand and of
course that's when all your processor
has come in I use sampling schemes
basing Kalman filtering predictive
coding belief propagation variational
message passing all of these are
processed there is which you really have
to you know commit to and I think at
that point then the game is is basically
what we all do with it in our daily
lives you know there's no great gift
there it's just having a framework that
highlights the connections between them
the other point you were making
which I'd haven't thought about before
was inverting the the way that one
defines the right sort of behavior in
terms of the outcomes and reward or cost
functions and is looking at that as real
way of writing down the kinds of things
that I do you know there are two
equivalent ways and I think formally
that probably you could articulate that
argument on the basis of the complete
class theorem so it's probably provably
true which means as you intimated II
it's a question of personal choice which
you which you commit to or you write
about all the rhetoric that you use the
world's one point though which I thought
deserved a bit more attention
you seem to have I was going to use the
word Elijah's but I can't baby you'll
certainly have alluded you have alluded
the epistemic part it is not the case
that expected free energy in its general
formalism can be reduced to a reward
function you have to have the
information gained on top so what that
means is that the rat in the maze has to
first explore to become familiar with
the maze before it becomes exploitative
in an RL sense so I would actually
challenge you that you're the Equality
which you are selling which i think is a
beautiful equality from the point of
view the complete classroom is a slight
misdirection because the whole point of
the free energy minimizing expected free
energy is it dissolves the exploration
exploitation dilemma thank you I was
just being lazy I mean of course like I
you know I completely left out
observations they were absent from those
equations for a reason because I feel
like they just getting away but that is
certainly part of it as well right their
information game was implicit what I was
trying to do is just make a very
specific link between reward and POW and
default policy but it would have been
included had I been more complete that's
all I have to say I'm just saying I was
being lazy there's sort of a high level
thank you well that's it really or
nothing else we're gonna hug it out in a
second he did he did a sure this is
gonna end in a hut so I'm gonna hold it
to that at the end well maybe just to
follow up on that some burning questions
from the audience one of which asked
explicitly does or can the free energy
be principled capture none or l-systems
and if not can it be considered unifying
you can't see that here it's coming on
this laptop so it does it capture non or
l-systems is that a way you'd phrase it
what you just described not capture non
reinforcement learning systems I think
it generalizes reinforcement learning so
that's one way of carving up that sort
of expected free energy is in terms of X
reward which we both wrote down as a lot
of probability or C for cost function
price I didn't meet you did so that
would certainly subsume all the
machinery conceptual mathematical that
you may want to bring to bear if you're
using RL by repeat that's not the
complete picture you need to equip that
RL like imperative with an information
game which is what I was referring to
with the Lindley experiment the
imperatives a good experimental design
that you know what in the absence of any
rewards there is still an imperative to
go and get good data that is good in the
sense of affording new information
resolving uncertainty and I think that
is exactly what you were talking about
in terms of the good surprise you know
it's a resolution of uncertainty
afforded by epistemic affordance which
mathematically would be the you know the
the thing that you'd have to add to an
RL cost function in order to get an
expected free energy but did you mention
inverse RL no you didn't I mean I
imagine that's another so twist on the
sociology which but I think to do that
properly you're gonna have to put
epistemic spurring the AIP specs back in
the resolution of uncertainty as a
fundamental part of the objective
function sometimes I miss aliens
sometimes known as novelty
I call it epistemic affordance cuz I
like that Giovanni Pazuzu so tell me
just call it that I do good and so
there's an well a question from Andre
but maybe is it following up on some of
these so there's questions on progress
for this field and in terms of how do
the models come about initially and how
do we go about carefully driving process
theories from these assumptions are
somehow inferring the P and Q from data
is that where we're going next then is
that something the theory has helped us
with or without narrow our
investigations
let me see the question yeah so this is
the how do you choose your P's and Q's
and theirs does not I don't have a I
don't have a quick and ready response I
can tell you what we do in practice
which is we try to come up with sensible
ones you know for example sparseness on
natural images or things like that and
we just see how and at the end of the
day we kind of just see how they work
right we see what sort of what sort of
things would be predicted what kind of
behavior is it consistent with behavior
we often use very simple tasks when we
talk about things like the Bayesian
brain so we have very simple peas and
very simple cues that are often drawn
that are often the actual peas from our
task right that's often how a Bayesian
brain experiment goes you as an
experiment or know what the pea is and
you're really testing to see if the
brain can figure that out too through
experience as for queues you know if
your optimal then your queue is just
your put your just your posterior
looking for causes of sub optimality is
how is one of the ways in which we can
identify the limitations of optimal
inference and that's how we would then
select our queues here's a simple
experiment so this is my favorite
experiment we talked about this one all
the time you're trying to do auditory
visual localization one possibility is
that you're doing it optimally so you
take into account uncertainty on both of
them another possibilities that you
don't and and so that would course so
that you do means that on every trial
your cue is a mean and a variance for
both audition to audition reloj
collation visualization and and if
you're not going to do it in Bayesian
way if we see that it's not coming from
behavior the explanation would be that
you're not tracking the variance on a
trial by trial base you have some kind
of fixed variance in mind ultimately I
think that's how you address these
questions right you build tasks for
which you can do the inversion you know
what the P is you look at the kinds of
deviations people have humans monkeys
whatever mice have from optimal behavior
and try to come up with explanations for
them by manipulating but by coming up
with restrictions on Q that says nothing
about the neural code so
hope that your question really wasn't
about that and then how did the models
arise in the first place so do we just
go back in early development of genetic
priors or are there any insights that we
can take from this principle for how
they arise the generative models that
you should showed were necessary for
this theory but not necessarily for M or
L based policy section so I mean the way
that you'd normally are frame those
questions in terms of hierarchical Bayes
so yes certainly you can look at
different time scales in terms of
evolution your development experience
dependent learning attentional control
synaptic efficacy right down to faster
actuations in responses to visual motion
as essentially being reflections of a
hierarchical genitive model where each
level of the hierarchy affords empirical
prize on on the level below and I guess
in some sense could be looked at as
doing a form of Bayesian model selection
so if you have a hierarchical model
questions like where did the prize come
come from again just go away so they
just come from the next level of and you
normally end up with the evolution of
the ugly as you intimated at the top
level but that's not to get out you then
compelled to model evolution as a
process or natural selection as a
process of Bayesian model selection and
it all comes then down to define the
relationship of the queue with the P but
the Q is now the phenotype and the P is
the environment and natural selection
now becomes a process of the environment
selecting those phenotypes that are fit
for purpose in terms of them being able
to model P the environment until you get
to humanity when we start to design our
own environments and then you get into
the world of eco niche construction and
free energy minimization underneath
illogical which which you can go there
if you want to so I'm not quite going to
agree with that because what you what
you've done is you've introduced yet a
third P that's why I have a subscript
for M right you said that P now there's
a third P the P is the way the world
actually works
which is in my view I mean call this I
know how many scientific anti-realists
are there out there like that's that's
inaccessible it's not a thing right the
only thing that you've got is what you
can store whether you're still unit in
your brain what you can compute that's
either what's in your brain or what's in
your genes
there is no P there is only a piece of
em you'll cut me out as a radical
skeptically oh yes I've done it before
this is like when every once in a while
someone says what's the most
controversial position you've ever taken
it's I'm not sure you guys exist I place
I place no metaphysical significance on
the latent variables of my models
I promise not to use philosophical terms
and I was violated I apologize so I'll
be the structural realist then if that
if that helps me so the position that I
would be forced to take it with which
probably is not what I'd want to if I
was in a controversy and is that there
is something real out there and it is
the P and the Q and the P that the Q is
predicated on the sort of implicit
Charenton model which I agree entirely
is not the real P it's not the
generative process is is constrained by
the real P out there
felis I think it's a really interesting
position because the whole sort of
inferring from within your the skull
when you just have access to data and
everything everything that you do is
based upon an inference about what's out
there that you'll never ever actually
directly connect with really does force
you into a skeptical position
philosophically the problem is that the
free energy really does depend upon the
goodness of those P's and Q's in the
head in relation to something that's
generating their sense of observation so
you sort of force back into a realist
position just to motivate the machinery
so philosophically it's very
uncomfortable for me but you are clearly
comfortable being a skeptic a skeptical
taking a skeptical position so that's
nice there's a really nice question here
and then will them go to Andre which is
well theories developed differently in
the context of the free energy framework
if this isn't a theory no they'll go on
with that
it's a length okay sorry Mike and
soapbox it's it's a language it's a way
of talking about theories of brain
function in my view it's a very useful
one but again we can shoehorn because of
the freedom to choose Pisa or P's and
Q's we can chew horn just about any
computational framework into it and so
no it would not develop differently
other than the fact that people might
start talking about reward a little
differently that's a possibility I think
that's been talking about reward and
default policy has been an exchangeable
might be a good thing it might be
helpful in some sense again it's
certainly the case that we measure
policies and we infer rewards and maybe
there'd be some benefit to that I don't
know so no one's made me a little strong
I'm just wondering I mean in a sense you
you intimated several ways that you
could use the framework just to
elaborate a whole bunch of process
theory is predicated on different kinds
of generative models but then you could
go to as a neuroscientist you could go
to the empirical data I'm one thing
that's hit me in the past few years is a
fundamental distinction between
generative models based upon discrete
space bases like Markov decision
processes and hidden hidden Markov
models and the like and those built
around the assumption you're dealing
with continuous states like Bayesian
filters can't predictive coding and the
like and just knowing that there are
different sorts of judgment what was a
carve in this way or that way I think
and can put a lot of very useful
constraints on the different hypotheses
or process theories that you could then
say well does it look as though the
brains doing this kind of message
passing or that kind of message passing
or both and then we can get into the
I'll grab the neural code what is what
messages are actually being passed and
how is it fit by physically represented
so I guess I'm agreeing with you that
the specification although the free
energy principle has nothing to say
about it when you start to commit to a
process theory and you start to commit
to the the generative model that will be
apt for this experimental power
you do actually narrow the hypothesis
space about the biophysics that would be
doing the you know the inference and
thus the kinds of behaviors and
neurophysiology that you would see from
that and then you just base it model
selection in the normal way to
adjudicate thanks for your presentation
so I think in both presentations we
focused a lot on the needs and also on
the Mystics and our physiologist mystics
actually also that's not my full
question I'll just say that we are then
fine then so we have the physicists and
the physiologist psychologists and so on
on the other side but in between the
Scruffy's we haven't discussed that very
much and of course a substantial part of
the conference are people from
engineering and that are trying to use
some of these principles to make better
models so I was wondering if the either
the free-energy principle or theory has
informed that engineering very practical
approach and if so how and the other
question because we're in an
interdisciplinary setting here it seems
like we are in a perfect setting to
explore the the confluence of those
three groups together and I was
wondering what you think we can actually
learn from each other and what the
interactions should be between the
Scruffy's the needs and the Mystics so
I'd be able to remember what those three
things are so Scruffy's were engineers
as I write needs were physicists what
was the third one
mystics mystics were philosophers and
then where were we putting the
physiologist with the mystics yeah
I don't know how the free-energy
framework particularly can bring these
groups together or explicate their
differences but I do see a general way
forward that is related to like the
Bayesian brain hypothesis which is that
the role of the engineers is to enhance
that's terrible
is to enhance our computational space of
models to give us more peas for which we
can find queues and actually do
inference so this is like saying we can
use artificial intelligence to help us
figure out maybe how real intelligence
works physiologist obviously provide the
constraints on what biology can do which
also tells us something about behavioral
you know the cues that are accessible I
think to some extent and philosophers
I'm sure there's one here all the ready
philosophers here philosophers can tell
us what the right words to use are do
you want to go for that one too also
someone has asked her car and minimize
my free energy by speaking a bit louder
okay sorry right this is very enjoyable
by the way keep it coming we're trying
to get be interested in your answer to
be quite honest when you do
electrophysiology you are well versed in
the active inference and some of some of
the maths so when you've got your
electrophysiology cap on do you regard
yourself as high-church theorist
theorist or are you are you are missing
I would have actually put you with with
the Scruffy's I think
electrophysiologists need to have a
formal understanding of the of the
system that they are trying to
characterize and they are in the game I
think of testing the process theories
that we've been talking about doing the
real heavy lifting but they need to be
able to appeal to some theoretical
framework in order to you know to
provide mathematical rigor to their an
hour season to that into their
conclusions my experiences that they
choose what works so that would that
would come bring them into the Scruffy's
camp and you're hearing the dialogue
here as to why it's good to be a neat or
perhaps you're not what do you think
yeah I like being in the with the
Scruffy's
doing something very practical yeah but
of course it has to be informed the the
the we have an infinite space of
possible experiment so we need to
basically use a theory to inform what
experiments we will do and even if a
theory is conceptual only conceptual its
you still need to have something to
ground yourself in as a physiologist I
was I was also wondering though just in
terms of the pure computational space
you know people from AI and so on
has there been any progress in using
free energy principles in that space and
if so could you talk about them a little
bit it's not my field but Mike's my
limited knowledge of it is it's making
more headway as one might imagine in
things like neuro robotics so we talked
about the construction real-world
artifacts so the on the purely software
side deep learning is the oil tanker
that is moving forward and that's what
everybody uses to be controversial I
think that's something exactly in the
wrong direction and it's obvious why
well sorry it should be obvious why I
say that not why it's in the wrong
direction and it's all about simplicity
it's always about carefully choosing the
smallest amount of data in the
algorithmically minimally complex way to
get to the same reduction of uncertainty
or increase in evidence so that means
the challenge is using small amounts of
data very carefully selected to solve
the problem that's not what current sort
of industry artificial intelligence is
interesting it's going exactly the other
direction exploiting the availability of
very large amounts of data labels
exploiting leveraging Moore's law and
actually celebrating the computational
complexity for me that's obscene because
the computational complexity is part of
the variation free energy it is
fundamental this variational principle
of least action so I haven't seen much
movement in that and indeed we have been
told by the couldn't great in charge of
the money in this
the you know some bright-eyed youngster
like you or something like me is not
going to change the direction of this
oil tanker that's where it's going but
in neurotics certainly is a non
industrial scale where you actually have
to make real things actively and to
engage in interact with the world
I see active inference making a much
more simple elemental and fundamental
difference you know just putting servers
and playful reflexes inferences planning
on top of existing robotics starting to
think more about sort of interpersonal
Dalek exchanges with robotics and the
like I say that's probably industry wise
making a difference from probably purely
engineering and engineering perspective
and just on the physics I've one
question here from Roth Hafner at the
University of Rochester who's asking
does the free energy principle also
apply to purely physical systems if so
how is it different from Hamilton's
principle of least action and if so what
does it add and if it does not apply to
purely physical systems wouldn't that
make it falsifiable after all and just
to mention there's been at least 10 or
15 people asking whether the theory is
falsifiable so maybe you could but the
falsifiable that's you know you
religiously not use the word scheme
you'd be very careful in the use of web
frameworks by potters yes so the free
energy principle the way this story was
told here was concise almost at the
point of being tie in cheek about you
know what the underlying equations are
what it would look like from the point
of view of biological sciences but the
back story is a version of Hamilton's
principle is at least actually don't
actually Hamilton's press release action
it but it is a variational principle of
least action it it certainly applies to
physical systems in fact we'll go a
little bit further it would say that
physical systems inherit from the same
variational principles that give rise to
the very to the free energy principle so
the idea is you've got this sort of
variational principles based upon
random dynamical systems when you have
random fluctuations that dominate those
you get quantum physics when you deal
with ensembles you get statistical
thermodynamics or more precisely
stochastic thermodynamics when you take
random fluctuations out of the game you
get classical mechanics and then you get
Lagrangian Newtonian mechanics and
Hamilton's Hamiltonians come to the fore
and when you put the Markov blanket
which we haven't spoken about but if we
frame this self-organization in terms of
inference you then get the bayesian
mechanics which is the free energy
principle so it doesn't explain physics
but it inherits from exactly the same
maths that quantum physics and other
physics explained again it's not
falsifiable it's not there to be
falsified it's not a theory that
requires evidence it's just a
mathematical truism clear well I've won
for Jeff here so so I'm out cuz I was
following up and which i think is an
interesting question which you've
touched on on ramstad a toss 20-19 work
our generative models better conceived
as encoded in the brain or enacted by
agent and environment where does the
model live if it has a subscript M it's
in your brain I think that's my short
answer it's it is part of the definition
it is part of the definition of your
computational energy is the set of
available generative models right and
then the other thing that's important is
the restrictions on the set of posterior
distributions that you're capable of
computing and representing so brain of
course as an extreme skeptic there is no
there is nothing outside of that so I
think that's why I have my answer that
I'm happiest I'd agree it's the free
it's the free energy gradients that
drive the dynamics you need to define
the generative model to define the
gradient but it's the gradient itself
that does the heavy lifting therefore
strictly speaking there is no genitive
modelled sub M it's just that ones which
would be necessary to explain the
gradient flows and the dynamic
he's frowning we found we found a bunch
of controversy sorry it sounds like
you're saying you don't need to know you
don't even even have a generative model
as long as you have the gradients I
think from the point of view of a
physicists that's probably right yes but
if you wanted to interpret what if I
don't want to do gradient descent I like
I like I like coordinates sent
personally and so those gradients are a
little different I think even with when
you move to a coordinate descent so I
don't mean to say that you can write
down a scheme that will optimize
something or self-organized your
particular attracting set of states in
the absence of generative model I'm just
saying the genitive model is a
mathematical construct that you will
only find it expressed in the machinery
doing the message passing the coordinate
descent or the gradient descent in the
brain itself
so you'll see reflections be like
cortical hierarchies in a hierarchical
general jente model the factorization
into wear and what into in terms of mean
field approximation of latent causes of
the sensory input but mathematically the
genitive model in our self does not
exist as a physical object is that still
true when you're doing model comparison
inside the brain because you have
multiple generative models that are
currently in sync because it seems to me
in that situation you do need to
evaluate the probability of the data
given each of your models for the
purpose of comparison which is that you
would need them
in some sense yeah I think it's true to
sense in what one is me trying to
observe your bread and trying to work
out what generative model you are
implicitly using sometimes said to in
tailing the old brain entails a
generative model to make it clear where
there's no commitment to a physical
instantiation or the genitive model it's
just the the message passing is
consistent with you using that guarantee
model so that would be me as a
neuroscientist looking at your brain and
trying to infer your Geritol model I
think from the point of view actually
using a journey of model that's a
slightly slightly which
a simpler situation which I'm sure you
can capture under your sceptical
position it says it's an interesting way
the question was framed you are we a
generative model or are we a process a
policy that can be described as if it
was optimizing a genitive model defined
by its priors since its sake it's a
subtle question and it comes back and
also irrelevant to the skeptic yes yeah
you'd have to worry about it but it is
consistent with your focus on defining
phenotypes in terms of the things they
do their policies so yeah you don't yeah
thing is a policy it is not the genitive
model that explains why you are doing
that planning as inference there's a
question here on Jeff's default policy
and from Roberto Ghoulie at Columbia who
says what's the reasoning behind
choosing default over prior so who gave
out you and how does it relate to the
ability to potentially update it if it's
a default right so you do update your
pop you do update your default policy as
soon as you receive sensory information
which was the part that was left out of
those particular slides which I've
already apologized the reason why I
don't use the phrase policy prior is
because of the visceral reaction that I
received from that man I mean that that
litter that literally is the whole
reason I mean so maybe so I think that
maybe someone should hand Zaca mic and
tell and ask him what what why why the
visceral reaction Carl you put up on the
on the screen Q of Pi which is a prior
over policies and Jeff you put up on the
screen P of s prime given s which is a
default dynamics those are two different
things and I don't know what the
relationship is between them but they're
different and our policy by itself is
the pulse the probability of choosing
actions given a belief state okay so if
I'd simply put a prior on a that's
already not a prior on a because I
changed notation halfway through if I'd
used PI and Q of PI instead of you
I could I would have been allowed to
call it a policy prior it was the way
that you it's the meaning of what you
were using the symbols were talking
about the default dynamics of the states
which is not what you do that's what you
assume happens when you're just letting
things go so that's equivalent to a
reward yes so in practice and not in my
example there is in fact a policy prior
you got to ask somebody else for that
one I don't know no because there is a
queue of pie right sorry there's a P of
pie and pie is empires a probability
distribution over distributions I could
take a vote from my point of view i I
just flipped in planning as inference
because it is to demystify all this sort
of epistemic very instrumental value in
the connection between our land and
optimal Bayesian decision theory the
expected free energy performance means
just planning as inference that's all it
is but it's just it incorporates both
the normal optimum Bayesian design the
Andreea as a little physiologist you are
complying with those principles when you
design your experiment you're working
out what data should I go and sample
solicit from my lab world you know to
reduce my uncertainty over the different
hypotheses that I am entertaining at the
moment and I think the answer was that
these frameworks provide the good
hypothesis space that means you don't
waste your time acquiring data that
doesn't resolve at the uncertainty the
queue of a PI's a posterior in fact so
planning as inference is just how would
you optimize your posterior beliefs
about what to do next
so PI is not a mapping between it's not
a straight action policy as in RL
optimal control theory where it's
actually a mapping between I'm in this
state and I have to do that so the
active interest rate is much more
general and deals with sequential policy
optimization where there are multiple
policies or sequences of actions in play
and they're denoted by Q and as you say
they have a posterior which means they
have to have a prior interesting in the
prior is though is the
the softmax function of the expected
free energy so from my point of view you
can have them but possibly not in the
sense that you were arguing about can I
just
so if active inference give us something
on top of reinforcement length is there
a class of tasks that would be solvable
by one framework or Theory versus the
other
yes sequential process optimization in
the case where you need to go in sample
data that will change your beliefs so I
noticed you use the word belief status a
lot of confusion about that so a belief
state is actually a state of belief that
has all the sufficient statistics
including the uncertainties and of
course to encode completely would
require you to have an infinite
dimensional Markov decision process to
do that so problems in which making that
move resolves uncertainty about what
would happen if I then did that so do I
go to a restaurant I do I go to the do I
make my own meal at home requires you
first to resolve the uncertainty about
whether you have the right ingredients
in your cupboard or in your fridge so
your policy has to incorporate your
belief state your primaries at the point
of acting knowing that your beliefs will
change as time goes on so there is no
strict RL scheme that can solve that
problem is easier sometimes then
reformulate mathematically RL could lead
to solutions of new paradigms
sorry formulation mathematical
formulation has a modest value that's my
comment so first of all I will
sheepishly admit to being reviewer too
but in my defense I don't think alive
living
I don't think alive
as a territory but I had a I had a real
question which goes back to
falsifiability
which I think a lot of people are
interested in here and and let me just
make sure I understood Jeff's proposed
experimental strategy so you're thinking
about defining some generative model
imposing it on an experimental subject
so that you can do you know what the
optimal policy is the optimal posterior
is and then looking for deviations and
thinking and trying to examine to what
extent you could explain those
deviations in terms of some restriction
on the posterior is that correct yes
yeah so so that strikes me as not being
a strategy for falsification because
assuming that the way in which you pick
yours you're looking for restrictions
such that your that when you minimize
free energy those restrict that that
restriction will saw will satisfy the
minimal free energy that's maybe the
implicit in the way that you've set it
up but maybe not it seemed to me that
what you really want to be doing is
impose the generative model separate or
at least separately elicit people's
assumptions about the generative model
and try to then characterize their prior
beliefs in terms of some restriction on
the variational family before they've
seen data right and then ask after
they've seen data would the posterior
within that restricted family reduced
free energy and it doesn't note that it
doesn't have to minimize free energy
because so that kind of short-circuits
the question about the algorithms
because even if you just take a gradient
step in that direction you're at least
reducing it but but if the free energy
ever went up if people ever chose a an
approximate posterior that increased
free energy that would be just I think
decisive falsification of the free
energy framework conditional on having
pinned down all the other pieces well
perhaps not like not enough samples is a
reason why free energy can blip up well
it depends how you mean when you're
talking about samples so there could be
a sample based variational Family but
that then that would be part of your
specification of the variational family
that you do in the first part of the
experiment or I think what you're saying
is may be that people are approximating
the free
the expectation with a bunch of samples
and they didn't take enough samples is
that that's one pot so I mean in my
experience there are two reasons why
free energy goes up it's usually because
that's the hardest thing to code up yeah
is the evaluation of free energy for me
personally so in other words it's a bug
and the other cause is is is because I'm
doing something that's time using some
kind of stochastic method mmhmm right
that's the only thing that ever causes
it to go up in my experience but then
again how would we evaluate that behave
really like I don't know wait I just
want to clarify your question yeah what
you're actually falsifying in the silly
example I gave is that the brain is
optimally Bayesian right No yeah yes but
well on the task right I could probably
it's pretty I can it I guarantee you
that there are some but in general right
you know there's plenty of examples
where the brain is not optimally
Bayesian right that's right interesting
question that's right those and those
are the interesting examples right
because that's where we can start like
nailing down the question okay the
falsifiable thing is is the brain
Apollonia Bayesian know now we need an
explanation there are a variety of
different explanations all many of which
take that would take two forms at least
within this framework right wrong P
wrong Q or severely limited Q and we
have to explore those we can do model
comparison to see which one is right
completely within this framework in
terms of right as in best fit to
behavior and that's that best you can do
so the thing is the funny thing about
type of falsifiability is that is that
to a large extent it's not like it this
is not a falsifiable theory most
theories of interest complicated
theories are not really falsifiable in
my opinion right it's really we would
love to live in that we would love to
live in I'm just gonna finish it it's
okay trust me I'm just gonna interrupt
you until I'm done I would love to live
in like a nice world of falsifiable
theories but at this point we don't have
any right we have descriptions of
behavior some are better than others and
we use model comparison to say this is
right this is wrong
very interesting that happens a lot of
times when we're looking at human
behavior is that there isn't a single
model that fits everybody it's
incredibly rare people use a variety
of different strategies to solve exactly
the same problem often with very minimal
differences in reward rates you know
it's talked about specifics later it's
not really important now so where does
that leave us that leave us with the
best description of behavior and again
this is now the skeptic talking one more
time last time I promised
oh crap Isis gets doubt and what I was
gonna say no that was okay yes
no okay at the end of the day science in
my opinion is about prediction and data
compression and not about truth it never
bothers me at all when there's a win up
when it when if when a hypothesis is not
falsifiable I only I really only care
about those two things and prediction is
really the only thing I can think and if
I'm marginalizing I mean that's the
automatic Occam's razor effective like
doing Bayesian inference right yeah you
got a bunch of models that are way over
parameterize they're total they're not
really useful so what do you do with
them low posterior probability they're
gone you're doing great prediction
because you've focused on the models
that actually work but my point was I
guess less about falsification and more
just about is there some distinctive
prediction specifically of free energy
you know that that is independent of the
particular choice of P and Q and the the
core prediction has to be that free
energy has to go down right and so to
fix so that so if it got you know if it
if it doesn't it's because I you're
using the wrong cue that's the sense in
which is not falsifiable this that's it
directly still on the board that SG is
you paraphrase slightly oh I see SG
easier good thanks more more on
falsifiability because I I would you
know if I can leave this debate and not
spend the next several years testing a
hypothesis that cannot be true or maybe
it's trivially true I would like to
avoid it so just to bring it back to
some of the work that we've seen today
you know the the the Scruffy's have
over the past several years a bunch of
neural networks they they take images
and they make do some computation and
they produce activity states and some of
them are generative and some of them are
not and one of the one of and what you
can do with each one of these networks
is take these activity States and
regress them onto the brain and you get
a prediction and right now one of the
neural networks that gives us really
accurate predictions reasonably accurate
predictions is Alex needs to
discriminate network and it's not
generative so I don't know I mean that
that's a hypothesis it could be true or
it could be false and so it seems like
one of the things that might be
falsifiable here is the assumption of a
that P of M lives in the brain because
there are other computing things that
are not generative models unless I'm
just not thinking about Alex node as
creatively as they need to I don't know
if it's a question of thinking
creatively if you were a scruffy you you
wouldn't eat her I mean Scruffy's is not
meant to be a derogatory term yeah I
think the majority of ours are Scruffy's
and but it certainly is easy to
reconceive those d convolutional
networks we saw in the last talk in
terms of an amortized inversion of a
generative model in fact there'd be a
very graceful set of schemes that you
could if he went to you to any
commercial AI company the odd that could
write down a variation altering code and
then amortize that and you would end up
with with the source of schemes and in a
sense and I love that presentation
because you know for me but what what
was being done was essentially different
forms of jointing models were being
assumed and they were being for
convenience amortize using current you
know deep learning architectures and
being put forward as working hypotheses
for a process theory for you know sort
of broad scale function anatomy heart
anatomy in the brain and you know
getting that right factorization I think
underneath the shape and the form of the
models and at what point of their
divergent ease of dual-task
face versus object these are exactly the
structure learning problems that are
presenting themselves when you don't
know the form of generative model so I
think it'd be quite easy to with the
right rosetta stone start to talk the
language that I would understand to
describe that very set of results but
you have to make the con you have to
understand that all of these deep
networks that you are just universal
function approximate is what are they
approximating the mappings that matter
what are the mappings of matter they are
mappings from data space to police
inferences they're just amortized
or summarizing learning how to infer how
to categorize how to predict how to and
all of that should at the end of the day
be described as a variational for energy
minimization thank you in the interest
of time and for the next session I'm
gonna ask our discussions if they're
satisfied and if they have any closing
statements satisfied I'm not satisfied
yet I'm still you ever be satisfied I'm
waiting for something very specific he
wants he's hot
okay they're gonna hug thank you all for
your patience of your tenants and your
great questions
[Applause]